A Guide to the Papers of Joseph D. Wood 1920-1951
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Papers of Joseph D. Wood 1920-1951
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 3
18 Hollinger Document Cases
Administrative Information
Access
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Burton deBerry Melchor III, in honor of his mother Margaret Wood, daughter of Captain Wood March 1, 1976.
Biographical/Historical Information
Joseph Downing Wood was born on February 22, 1867, on a farm in Washington Co., North Carolina. He was the first of nine children born to Samuel and Pattie Downing Wood. He left the family farm in 1886 to seek his fortune in Norfolk, Virginia. Here he found work as an apprentice seaman, largely on coastal ships. By the age of 21, he was a licensed seaman and at 23, a master seaman on a tugboat. By 1900 Wood had risen to the position of Yard Pilot for the Norfolk Navy Yard in Portsmouth. During World I he was commissioned as a Lt. Commander in the Navy Reserve and served as director of tugs and all floating equipment in the Fifth Naval District.
After the war Wood founded his towing company, beginning with one tug and one barge, neither of which was paid for. By the time he sold his Wood Towing Corporation for $1,500,000 in 1951, the company controlled a whole fleet of tugs. Wood had sold his business rather than agree to the demands of his employees for unionization.
Wood was almost 60 when he first entered the political arena and was elected to the Norfolk City Council in 1926. He was reelected to the council in 1934, 1938, and 1942. He became ex-officio mayor of Norfolk when he was elected president of the council in September, 1940. Wood served as mayor, until his retirement from politics in 1944, during an extremely busy period for a defense oriented city like Norfolk. Economy was Wood's watchword as a politician. Being a staunch conservative, he firmly believed in the "pay as you go" philosophy, which dominated Virginia politics during the period in which he was active.
Joseph Downing Wood married Ada Estelle Burnell on June 2, 1896. They had one child, Margaret (Mrs. Burton DeBerry Melchor). Wood died on April 16, 1959.
Scope and Content Information
Captain Wood was president of Wood Towing Corporation (Tugboats), a member of the Norfolk City Council (1926-1930, 1934-1944), and mayor of Norfolk (1940-1944). He also served on a number of public boards, most notably the Elizabeth River Tunnel Commission. His papers, dating from 1920 to 1951, are divided into five sub-groups: personal, public service (non-political), business, mayoral files, and City of Norfolk data. The personal papers contain some family genealogy, correspondence, his autobiography, and a variety of financial records. The public service papers deal mainly with his service on the Elizabeth River Tunnel Commission. The business papers consist of correspondence, tug repair estimates and labor relations files. The bulk of the mayoral files are correspondence, while the City of Norfolk material focuses on financial data and is not duplicated by material found at Norfolk City Hall. Where possible Captain Wood's own filing system was followed.
Organization
The papers, dating from 1920 to 1951, are divided into five sub-groups: personal, public service (non-political), business, mayoral files, and City of Norfolk data. Where possible Captain Wood's own filing system was followed.
Contents List
- Personal Papers
  - Financial Papers
    - Annual Reports: Westinghouse 1931 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Annual Reports: West Penn Electric 1946 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Annual Reports: American Waterworks &Electric Co. 1946 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Autobiography: Sowing and Reaping 1951 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Brokers' Statements and Receipts-Livingston and Co.; Post and Flagg 1933 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Brokers' Receipts-Post and Flagg 1936 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Brokers' Statements and Receipts-Post and Flagg; Dyer, Hudson &Co. 1937 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Brokers' Statements and Receipts-Thomson Dyer, Hudson Post &Flagg 1938 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Brokers' Statements and Receipts-Thomson &McKennon 1939 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Brokers' Statements and Receipts-Thomson Abbott, Proctor &Paine 1940 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Brokers' Statements and Receipts-Thomson Abbott, Proctor &Paine 1941 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Brokers' Statements and Receipts-Abbott, Proctor &Paine 1942, 1944, 1945, 1947-49 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Brokers' Statements and Receipts-Abbott, Proctor &Paine 1950 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Cancelled Checks (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Cancelled Checks (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Cancelled Checks (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Cancelled Checks (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Cancelled Checks (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Cancelled Checks 1946 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Cancelled Checks 1947 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Cancelled Checks 1948 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Cancelled Checks 1949 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Cancelled Checks 1950-1951 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence 1935-1950
    - Correspondence November 1935-December 1939 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence 1941-1944 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence 1945-1946 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence 1947 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence February-December 1948 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence 1949 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence 1950 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Birthday Cards 1950 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Family
    - Family Geneology (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Federal Tax Records 1920-1929 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Federal Tax Records 1931-1935 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Federal Tax Records 1936-1939 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Federal Tax Records 1940-1941 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Masonic Lodge Material: Correspondence; 1924 Directory; Membership Certificate (1925) 1924, 1925 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Personal Papers (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Norfolk-Proposed Federal Taxation of State Bonds
    - Norfolk City Tax Returns 1937-1940 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Norfolk Auto License 1929, 1931, 1934-1935, 1937-1940, 1942, 1944, 1950 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Norfolk City Real Estate Tax Receipts 1928-1935, 1938-1940 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Norfolk City and Virginia State Personal Property and Poll Tax Receipts 1927-1934, 1938, 1940-1946, 1950 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Personal Receipts 1923, 1931, 1936, 1937 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Personal Receipts 1938 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Personal Receipts 1939 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Personal Receipts 1940 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Personal Receipts 1941 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Personal Receipts 1942 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Personal Receipts 1943-1944 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Personal Receipts 1945-1946 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Personal Receipts 1947-1951 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Photograph: Memorial to War Dead of Norfolk County 1929 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Photograph: J.D. Wood on Right (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Princess Anne County Real Estate Tax Receipts 1928-1930 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Proposed Federal Taxation of State and Municipal Bonds-Speech by Solicitor General Henry Epstein 1939 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Taxation-Virginia
    - Taxation Publications (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Tecumseh Beach Property Condemnation 1941-1947 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Virginia State Income Tax Records 1922-1929 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Virginia State Income Tax Records 1930, 1932-1943, 1945, 1946, 1950 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 4)
- Public Service
  - American Christian Palestine Committee 1946-1949 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Berkley Bridge Purchase Correspondence 1932-1933 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Bill Creating the Elizabeth River Tunnel District (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Bills Before Delaware General Assembly in re. Delaware (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Bonney Home for Girls Correspondence 1949-1950 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Bridge/Tunnel Newspaper Clippings 1941-1942, 1944 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Brooklyn Battery Crossing Report 1939 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Child Welfare League 1946 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Elizabeth River Tunnel: Correspondence 1926-1933 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Elizabeth River Tunnel: Correspondence September-December, 1941 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Elizabeth River Tunnel: Correspondence 1942 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Elizabeth River Tunnel: Correspondence 1943 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Elizabeth River Tunnel: Correspondence 1944 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Elizabeth River Tunnel: Correspondence 1945 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Elizabeth River Tunnel: Correspondence 1946-1949 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Elizabeth River Tunnel: Correspondence 1950 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Elizabeth River Tunnel Revenue Bond Act 1942 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Elizabeth River Tunnel Traffic Survey and Estimated Revenues 1947 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Elizabeth River Tunnel-Engineers Report (Abbott, Merkt &Co.) 1941 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Elizabeth River Tunnel:Engineers Reports on Various Highway Projects (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Elizabeth River Tunnel: U.S. Army Corps of Engineers Hearing 1945 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Elizabeth River Tunnel: Engineers Reports on Various Tunnels 1940 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Elizabeth River Tunnel: Mobile, Ala. Tunnel Clippings 1940-1941 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Elizabeth River Tunnel: New York City Narrows Tunnel Report 1945 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Elizabeth River Tunnel: Sketches of Bridge Tunnel Complex and Bridge (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Elizabeth River Tunnel Commission: Engineers' Report 1947 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Elizabeth River Tunnel Revenue Bond Act May 1950, July 1950 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Florence Crittenden Home 1944-1950 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children 1931-1935 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Temporary Wartime Resources Committee 1941 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Travelers Aid 1941-1943 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 15)
  - United Seaman's Service Inc. 1943 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 16)
- Business Papers
  - Army Base Surroundings 1943 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Blocking Measurments on Wood Towing Co. Equipment (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Business Publications and Memoranda (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Coast Guard Distress Regulations and Area Map 1933 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Copper Recovery Corporation (War Production Board) 1942-1943 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, General 1923-1946 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Shipyard Wage Rates January 1944 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Crandell Dry Dock Engineers 1941 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Fairbanks, Morse &Co. Proposal 1941 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Hampton Roads Maritime Exchange 1933-1935 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Harbor at Assateague 1922-1924 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Opinions, Laws, Legal Briefs re: Towing Rules, Boats, Labor 1927,1932,1946 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Repair Estimate: M.S. Brilliant 1931 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Speeches (Business Related) (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Standard Transportation Co. vs. Wood Towing Corp: Briefs Filed in U.S. District Court of Appeals 1933 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Steamboat Inspection Laws: Correspondence; Rules Book 1922-1925 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Steel Tug Specifications (85 Foot) 1943 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 4)
  - "Women's Contributions in the Field of Invention"-U.S. Dept. of Labor 1923 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 5)
- Mayoral Files
  - Correspondence
    - Collection of Scrap Aluminum June-July 1941 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence 1940 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence January-March, 1941 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence April, 1941 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence May, 1941 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence June, 1941 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence July, 1941 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence August-September, 1941 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence October, 1941 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence November, 1941 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence December, 1941 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence January, 1942 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence February, 1942 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence March, 1942 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence April, 1942 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence May, 1942 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence June, 1942 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence July, 1942 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence August, 1942 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence September, 1942 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence October, 1942 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence November, 1942 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence December, 1942 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence January, 1943 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence February-March, 1943 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence April, 1943 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence May-June, 1943 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence July, 1943 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence August, 1943 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence September, 1943 (Box-folder Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence October, 1943 (Box-folder Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence November-December, 1943 (Box-folder Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence January, 1944 (Box-folder Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence February-March, 1944 (Box-folder Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence April-May, 1944 (Box-folder Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence June-July, 1944 (Box-folder Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence August, 1944 (Box-folder Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence September-October, 1944 (Box-folder Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Forms to Use in Calling Out Virginia Protective Force 1941 (Box-folder Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Mayors of Norfolk from 1736 to 1918 and 1918 to 1940 (Box-folder Box 16, Folder 4)
- City of Norfolk Material
  - City Goverment Organization Chart 1926 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Consolidation Efforts of Area-Wide Cities (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence re. City Charter, 1930-1933; Copy of Charter 1930-1933 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Financial Data re. City 1934-1935, 1937-1939 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Hampton Roads Sanitation District Report 1936 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Industrial Commission: Report on Fresh Water 1926 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Maps of Norfolk &Portsmouth Belt Line R.R. 1927 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Memoranda re. City of Norfolk 1944 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Norfolk city Building Zone Map with Ordinance 1924 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Norfolk City Finances, Reports: Fiscal Year 1917 1917 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Norfolk City Finances, Reports: Fiscal Years 1921, 1922 1921, 1922 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Norfolk City Budget Estimates: Fiscal Year 1924 1924 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Norfolk City Budget Appropriations: Fiscal Year 1924 1924 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Norfolk City Budget Estimates: Fiscal Year 1925 1925 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Norfolk City Finances, Reports: Fiscal Year 1925 1925 (Box-folder Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Norfolk City Budget Appropriations: Fiscal Year 1926 1926 (Box-folder Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Norfolk City Finances, Reports: Fiscal Year 1926 1926 (Box-folder Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Norfolk City Finances, Reports: Fiscal Year 1928 1928 (Box-folder Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Norfolk City Budget Estimates: Fiscal Year 1929 1929 (Box-folder Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Norfolk City Budget Estimates: Fiscal Year 1930 1930 (Box-folder Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Norfolk City Budget: Fiscal Year 1931 1931 (Box-folder Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Norfolk City Budget: Fiscal Year 1933 1933 (Box-folder Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Norfolk City Budget Estimates: Fiscal Year 1934 1934 (Box-folder Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Port Authority: Map of Hampton Roads 1932 (Box-folder Box 18, Folder 9)
- Political
  - Campaign Expenses 1924 (Box-folder 19:1)
  - Campaign Materials 1924 (Box-folder 19:2)
  - Campaigns - Precinct Returns 1924 (Box-folder 19:3)
  - Clippings - Mainly 1924 Council Elections 1924 (Box-folder 19:4)
  - Correspondence 1924, 1926, 1934 (Box-folder 19:5)
  - Correspondence 1945-1950 (Box-folder 19:6)
  - Councilman Election 1926 (Box-folder 19:7)
  - Councilman Election 1940 (Box-folder 19:8)
  - Councilman Election 1942 (Box-folder 19:9)
  - Councilman Election 1944 (Box-folder 19:10)
  - New Deal 1943 (Box-folder 19:11)
  - List of Precincts / Precinct Leaders undated (Box-folder 19:12)
  - Publications 1925, 1934 (Box-folder 19:13)
  - Recall Action 1928 (Box-folder 19:14)
  - League of Virginia Municipalities Certificate undated (Box-folder 19:15)
  - Speeches (Folder #1) undated (Box-folder 19:16)
  - Speeches (Folder #2) undated (Box-folder 19:17)